<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held at Chelmsford in the county of Essex, September 2d, 1691 before the Honourable Sir William Dolben, Knight, one of the justices of the Court of Kings Bench by Stephen Thornton ...</title>
            <author>Thornton, Stephen, 1657 or 8-1744.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16613</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13153486</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13153486</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 752:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assizes held at Chelmsford in the county of Essex, September 2d, 1691 before the Honourable Sir William Dolben, Knight, one of the justices of the Court of Kings Bench by Stephen Thornton ...</title>
                  <author>Thornton, Stephen, 1657 or 8-1744.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 28.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Amos V, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98130:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98130:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES HELD AT CHELMSFORD IN THE <hi>County of Eſſex. <hi>September</hi>
               </hi> 2d. 1691.</p>
            <p>Before the Honourable Sir <hi>WILLIAM DOLBEN,</hi> Knight, one of the JUSTICES of the Court of KINGS BENCH.</p>
            <p>By <hi>STEPHEN THORNTON,</hi> Rector of <hi>Ludſdown</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98130:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98130:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Coll. John Cook, High Sheriff for the <hi>County of Eſſex.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Could have eaſily ſate down contented with the good Reception this Performance found upon the place; nor am I ignorant how impolitick it is to puſh on too far upon the Flatteries of an happy beginning; but as your Commands alone drew me from my private Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo they have prevaled with me to be yet more Publick. If any thing prove worthy of blame in this Attempt, you muſt be pleaſed to be in a great meaſure anſwerable for it, with thoſe other Gentlemen who would not be denied, and indeed whoſe Kindneſſes have merited this and a greater Obedience.</p>
            <p>I confeſs it is ſomething uneaſie to think of being expoſed to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Men, which are not commonly ſo fair as they ſhould be. But let them be what they will, I ought to gratifie you at ſome hazard; and for once will try the Ingenuity of the World, in hope that what is here ſaid may benefit ſome part of it.</p>
            <p>Not being converſant in Modern Writings, perhaps I have ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here but what ſome others have ſaid better before me. If any know where, they have my leave to repair thither, and my Prayers for a Bleſſing upon their Applications. I would not willingly be acceſſary to any man's loſs of time and diſappointment. But I hope they will allow me a Province among thoſe of leſſer Reading and Attainments. And I aſſure you, <hi>Sir,</hi> there are thoſe in the World to whom the things here ſpoken are new, and ſome of them ſuch as pretend to converſe and talk of Books, and from whom one might expect other things. Writing would be at a ſtand, were every one bound to produce ſomething <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly</hi> new, the Actions of the World being little elſe but a ſeries of Repetitions.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98130:3"/>
            <p>I never had the Vanity to think of pleaſing all Men; on the contrary, I certainly reckon upon it that I ſhall diſpleaſe ſome. Perhaps too the fault will be on their ſide, which I pray God to forgive them. If any ſhall deſire to triumph in my Infirmities, I ſhall prevent them in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Diſcovery, being alway ready to make a large confeſſion of them. But if an honeſt Intention may make amends, let them know that I am a great lover of Mankind, and when I pleaſe them leaſt, I deſire to do them good. God grant this Performance may attain that end, and I have mine.</p>
            <p>That thoſe who are skilled in Criticks may not think themſelves neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, I will excuſe one thing to them. Perhaps ſome things may ſeem to be brought into this Diſcourſe impertinently. It may be neceſſary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to tell them, That my Text was not only thoſe few words of the Prophet prefixt to the Sermon, but the temper of the World as it fell un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Obſervation. And if they think I ought not to have accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated my thoughts to it, it may be ſufficient to tell them, that I am of another mind, and if in an Error, not paſt all hopes of being made ſenſible of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I beg your Pardon if I have done you any diſhonour in this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, and ſhall take this Occaſion publickly to acknowledge my Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to your ſelf and Relations, to whom I owe the Opportunities which I have of ſerving the Church of God. That you may continue immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the love which I know you have to our eſtabliſhed Church, and your largeneſs of Soul towards all good Chriſtians; That you may ſtill become your Honourable Station, and find returns of all in this and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, is the hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Moſt Humble and Moſt Obliged Servant, STEPHEN THORNTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98130:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>AMOS V.XV.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Hate the evil, and love the good, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Judgment in the gate: it may be that the Lord God of Hoſts will be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious unto the Remnant of <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BY the Complaints that make ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a part of this Prophecy we underſtand, That the Kingdom of the Ten Tribes was at this time fallen into great Corruptions of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and <hi>Civil Juſtice.</hi> For as if it had been but a light thing to walk in the ways of <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat,</hi> who had taught them to ſin, they had multiplied their Impieties, and made the Abominations of <hi>Gilgal</hi> and <hi>Beerſheba</hi> as Famous as thoſe of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel, ver.</hi> 5. The bitterneſs of their Judgment, their Exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Poor, the Affliction of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and taking Bribes, make up the reſt of their Character in this Chapter, to ſuch a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſion of Juſtice, that it was become a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thing to keep ſilence, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. rather than to be waſted with delays, to diſſemble an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98130:4"/> rather than ſuffer a greater in form of Law.</p>
            <p>All then ſeem to be ſilent but their ſins, and the Prophet, who diſcharges his Office at that rate, that <hi>the Land was not able to bear his words, Chap.</hi> 7.10. Indeed the Land was not in caſe to bear much ſearching, and the poor Man found by his Reception, that he had not much changed his Employment, when <hi>the Lord took him from among the Herdſmen to make him a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ver.</hi> 14. but had now as ſenſeleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to deal with as thoſe he had fed in the Fields of <hi>Tekoa.</hi> Yet no fear of diſturbing the Land, which deſired to be left in a quiet Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, nor any conſtruction of diſreſpect to the <hi>King's Court and Chappel, ver.</hi> 13. can make him ſuppreſs a Divine Meſſage, but he fills them with Reproofs, Lamentations, and Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of approaching Judgment, and ſometimes clears up into a milder Exhortation with Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of Mercy; of which latter ſort is the Text now under conſideration, <hi>Hate the evil, and love the good,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe words, <hi>Hate the evil, and love the good,</hi> are in themſelves of a large ſignification, but compared with the 6th. and 14th. Verſes, and the occaſion of the Diſcourſe, they ſeem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of this limited ſenſe, <hi>viz. Be Religious.</hi> To <hi>eſtabliſh Judgment in the Gate,</hi> is to <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98130:4"/> Publick Juſtice,</hi> which in thoſe Times and Countries was done at the Gates of Cities. By <hi>Joſeph</hi> he underſtands the <hi>Ten Tribes,</hi> which it ſeems the <hi>Syrian</hi> Wars and other Calamities had now reduced to a Remnant. And the Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>it may be,</hi> imports no diſtruſt of God's Mercy (for never any one ſo perſwades Repentance), but is an artificial propounding of a Difficulty, to heighten and warm their Applications.</p>
            <p>I ſhall enlarge the ſenſe of the Prophet into this general Propoſition; <hi>That beſide the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Obligations to Religion and Juſtice, there is that of the greateſt Intereſt we have in the World,</hi> viz. <hi>The Eſtabliſhment of a Nation in the favour of God, and ſecuring the Publick Happineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſhall firſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the common Obligations to it; then that of National Intereſt; and laſtly, a Modern Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Common Obligations to <hi>Religion</hi> are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It's Authority. This is that ſhort way of Satisfaction ſo much in eſteem with ſome of the Philoſophers, who ſaved themſelves the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of Reaſoning by the Authority of their Maſters. And what is this ſetting up Men for Gods, but worſhipping Error and Impertinence?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98130:5"/> But if the Authority be truly Divine, it ſelf is the higheſt Reaſon. Now that the Religion which we profeſs has ſuch an Authority, was demonſtrated by thoſe Perſons who were entru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the propagation of it in the World, not by the pretence of ſecret Conferences with <hi>Nymphs,</hi> or reſort to far diſtant <hi>Oracles</hi> (as in the known Stories of <hi>Numa</hi> and <hi>Lycurgus</hi>), but by the active Preſence of a Divine Power with them in their Miniſtry, and by a Conduct that might clear their Sincerity to Mankind. It would be too much to ſend thoſe that deny this ſo many Ages backward (they are commonly too weak and lazy to travel ſo far after an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment); let them then but look about them at the Progreſs that this Religion has made in the World, and give a tolerable account how all this could come to paſs without ſuch a Divine Power. None ſpeak more of the dulneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politeneſs of the Apoſtles than they. With what a ſpiteful ſort of ſatisfaction are the Characters of the ſame Vertue in <hi>Seneca</hi> admired, in St. <hi>Paul</hi> blaſphemed? How have ſome Heathen Writers in their judgment for fineneſs of Wit and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion out-done the Teachers of Chriſtianity? Caſt into this Account all the Contempts the <hi>Corinthians</hi> treated their Apoſtle with (thô the moſt learned of them all,) <hi>his preſence weak,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98130:5"/> (perhaps <hi>homo tricubitalis) his ſpeech contemptible,</hi> without any graces of Oratory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all their little Witticiſms upon the Apoſtles mean Accompliſhments and way of Life. And what does all this come to, but that it proves them aſſiſted with a Divine Power? 'Tis true, <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Seneca, &amp;c.</hi> ſpoke fine things concerning Vertue and Felicity, but who ever heard of their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the World? A <hi>Fiſherman,</hi> under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of Drunkenneſs, with a plain inartificial ſpeech, brings in 3000 Souls, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. A <hi>Tent-maker</hi> ventures to Preach at <hi>Athens,</hi> the Seat of Learning; and the Mechanick finds Proſelytes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Philoſophers, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. Look into the preſent ſtate of the World, and where-ever there is Learning and Civility, the Writings of theſe Men are kept, are reverenced, are conſulted as Oracles. Never was Philoſophy, Wit, all Science ſo far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced; and yet the wiſeſt and moſt accompliſh'd of the Age grow old in ſtudying theſe Apoſtles, nor has all <hi>Tully</hi> ſo much Comment as one Paragraph of the Tent-maker. It will be hard to perſwade any conſidering Man, that all this could proceed from Men of their Figure without the help of a Divine Power. St. <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledges that <hi>this treaſure was put into earthen veſſels,</hi> and makes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of it in favour of the Goſpel, <hi>that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the power might be of God, and not of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98130:6"/> men,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.7. We muſt then confeſs a Miracle on one hand; for either thoſe attributed to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles are true, or elſe the ſucceſs of Chriſtianity will it ſelf be the greateſt Miracle that ever was in the World. And take which ſide you will, it proves the Divine Authority of our Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Nature of the things it propounds, which are of the greateſt Conſequence to us imaginable. The higheſt Enquiry of our Life is after Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">
                  <p>De Finib. l. <hi>5.</hi> — id eſſe in bonis ultimum ſecundùm natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram vivere. — Ex hominis na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turâ undique perfectâ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>— Omnes ſapientes eſſe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos, ſed tamen fieri poſſe ut ſit alius alio beatior.</p>
               </note> and this <hi>Chriſtian Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> kindly offers us her Hand in the Search. <hi>Cicero</hi> (whom I mention for a Pattern) has a whole Treatiſe of Beatitude, wherein beſide ſome Learning in ſorting the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Ancients, we find little of any thing poſitively aſſerted, but <hi>That our ſupream Good is to live according to perfect Nature,</hi> and that all <hi>Wiſe Men are happy, but in ſeveral degrees.</hi> This goes a good way toward a Confeſſion that Beatitude is to be expected in ſome other ſtate. But indeed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was the weakneſs of that Philoſophy, that it ſtill left Men upon the Confines of Felicity.</p>
            <p>But a moderate Proficient in revealed Religion knows more than a whole Age of Philoſophers. From what cauſe proceed the Miſeries that vex and embitter Humane Life, what allays may be given to them here, what Corrections of Nature,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98130:6"/> what approaches to be made to the Divine and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Life; That our Souls are immortal, and ſhall ſubſiſt in another ſtate, wherein they ſhall better know what belongs to Felicity; What Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations the Supream Being has made of himſelf and his Love to the World, how to underſtand and ſubmit to his Providences, and make uſe of all the parts of Life; what hope we have of Mercy, and what aſſiſtance of a Divine Grace; by what Duties we may pleaſe and enjoy our Creator; theſe are Propoſitions of our Religion. And how wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy are theſe to employ our moſt ſerious Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? It is only in ſuch that our Minds are match'd with an Object. What was Heavenly in them expires while they mingle too freely with the Duſt. Let our thoughts then ariſe and ſoar to the utmoſt reaches of our Nature, and let us di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh our ſelves from the Brutes, leaving them their own Enjoyments. Nothing but Religion can ſufficiently vindicate us from being part of the Herd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Its Reaſonableneſs. This joyned to its Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is wonderfully obliging, without which that might ſeem Tyranny over the Soul; but this brings the engagement of Love. Now Religion is Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal as to Points of <hi>Faith. That God is,</hi> is as certain as that there is a World, as that there is a Cauſe which it ſelf is not alſo the Effect of ſomething
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98130:7"/> elſe. He that knows his own frame, finds a great many ſteps of a Divine Wiſdom that has been there. Reaſon it ſelf is one of the greateſt Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and its own Argument of a God. The great thoughts of a Soul ſhew a great Original, and it can conceive no leſs of its Powers, but that there is a Being who has them in perfection. It ſelf is a little Deity governing its own World, which muſt needs facilitate the belief of ſomething parallel in the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>And as it is evident from Reaſon <hi>that God is,</hi> ſo that <hi>He is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him,</hi> Heb 11.6. and conſequently that there is a future ſtate. And thô we were not agreed upon Revelation as to the neceſſity of a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> it would be no irrational Belief. We can't but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Debt of a perfect Obedience to our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and yet all find a ſtrange Iniquity in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (which God placed not there, and therefore is not bound to make allowances for) which ſtains the beſt Life and the cleareſt Duties. The Sacrifices of all Nations have been a kind of Confeſſion that this needed Blood. And indeed if on one hand we conſider Sin in all its horrors, and on the other the Purity and Juſtice of God, we may as ſoon bring Antipathies together as God and Man without a Mediator. The Afflictions of this Life, were they evenly diſtributed, would be far from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98130:7"/> clearing our Accounts with Divine Juſtice; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are not ſo, therefore cannot be relied upon as Satisfactions. And whatever ſome may think of the vertues of a true Repentance, come to matter of Fact, and there is none ſo true, but, if it ſtand alone, it ſelf is a thing to be repented of, needs a Sacrifice, and leads to a Redeemer.</p>
            <p>The other parts of <hi>Faith,</hi> which are a train of Propoſitions from theſe two, <hi>There is one God,</hi> and <hi>One Mediator between God and Man,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. will be Rational becauſe they are ſo. And I know not why we ſhould be afraid of that way of ſpeaking, <hi>That the Myſteries of this Religion are rational too,</hi> ſince this cannot be denied of things <hi>above Reaſon,</hi> ſo they are not <hi>contrary</hi> to it, which whoever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms concerning the <hi>Revealed Acts</hi> of an infinite, incomprehenſible Nature, is himſelf moſt irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. And perhaps ſome of theſe things which are above Reaſon in its preſent ſtate, may not be ſo much Secrets to us in another, when <hi>we ſhall know as we are known,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. nor perhaps are ſo now to ſome higher Reaſons in the World.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Active part of our Religion</hi> is reduced by our Saviour to the exerciſes of <hi>Love to God and our Neighbour,</hi> which are ſo confeſſedly Rational, that all Moraliſts of good Credit have, thô in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent terms, uſed them as Principles. Therefore to be ſhort with them, if that be Rational which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98130:8"/> makes us like God, and admits us into his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which employs and advances our diviner part, and renders us profitable in the World; then nothing can be more Rational than Religion. Thus have I conſidered ſome of the common Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall urge the <hi>Obligation</hi> of <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I call this our greateſt Intereſt, and indeed it is little to none but thoſe whoſe Souls are ſuch. Other Creatures have a Principle that directs them to preſerve their own Being, but Man is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, capable of a Publick Care. Nay, we might conſider the Community ſo too, a Great Animal, whereof we are all parts, living by one common Soul. And as it is unnatural that <hi>one of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſhould rejoyce whilſt the reſt ſuffer,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26; ſo in this great Body none ſhould have a Felicity by himſelf. 'Tis monſtrous that the Caſe of the whole ſhould not be the Caſe of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. By this our private Reſpects are to be tried. The love of Parents in compariſon with that of our Country ſcarce deſerves the name of Vertue; nor our fondneſs of Princes, but as they are a Common Good; otherwiſe it is but a private Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, to ſay no worſe of it. I believe it is our Duty to love our Country above any one part of it. It is hard to think of this and not be a little
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98130:8"/> warm againſt an unnatural Generation amongſt us that would ſell us. We have many that ſpeak half <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> enough to make it queſtioned whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fathers. But I will leave them to other hands to be treated ſuitably to their Merits, and <hi>ſhew how Religion ſerves this Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By a <hi>Natural Influence,</hi> inaſmuch as it <hi>makes good Citizens.</hi> Fear might indeed bring Men into Society, but there muſt be ſome other Principle to keep them together. That makes them a great heap of People, but Love cements and unites them. Without this, Society is but a more ſly ſtate of War, and Compacts are but Snares to them that hold them Sacred. Now whatever tends to Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Juſtice, Sobriety, Contentment, love of Peace and Common Good, is the Dictate of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whoſe Kingdom is in the Minds and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, and makes them not only a Society, but Sociable. A People is ſecure under Governours that fear God of good Laws, and thoſe in good hands; that they ſhall enjoy their Labours, and find the Protection they pay for. They would know their meaning in their Solemn Profeſſions, and not fear their having Intereſts diſtinct from their People. On the other hand, a Prince does not find that Service from his own Laws as from Religion. Obedience from an inward Principle needs not the quickning of Legal Penalties, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98130:9"/> moves by an everlaſting Spring, and ſcorns to ſtay for Motives that were invented for Slaves and Cattel. Men would more freely pay for their ſhare in the Publick Safety, and redeem it out of ſome Chargeable Vanity. Religion would cut off Murders, Invaſions of Right, and all Diſorders at the Root, and leave no work for the Law; and this, by taking away Envy, unlawful Deſires, and ſoftning the Genius of Men: yet makes them not ſo ſoft as to ſhrink from their Stations in a Juſt War, when their Country requires their Service. That's the effect of Vice and Luxury. Theſe will make Men great Souldiers in Peace, to diſtinguiſh themſelves now and then in a fit of drunken Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, but dare not ſee an Enemy ſober; and whilſt others ſpend their Blood and Reſt for their Country, theſe lye inglorious at home, diſſolved and diſpirited by a corrupt Life. It's for want of a due ſenſe of Religion among Men, that a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, notwithſtanding the Caution of Oaths and Teſts, ſcarce knows her own.</p>
            <p>I know that accidentally the true Religion <hi>brought a ſword upon earth, Mat.</hi> 10.34; Pretences to it have hurried Men into Immoralities; and ſome falſe Religions have very Caſuiſtically deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined them Lawful. But let this be laid to the Vices, and Paſſions, and Prepoſſeſſions of Men, which where Religion could not reform, it irritated.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98130:9"/> Some from the hot advices of theſe fill the World with Deſolation, and call it Religion; and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhing <hi>Fool, that ſays in his heart, there is no God,</hi> cants <hi>Lucretius, Tantum Relligio potuit,</hi> &amp;c. Certainly men would think it hard to be dealt with in their own Reputations as they deal with that <hi>Wiſdom which is from above, pure, peaceable, James</hi> 3.17. no Parent of Strife or Ruin: its Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes and Pretences indeed may be ſo, but it ſelf is naturally fitted to the Happineſs of Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it <hi>procures God to be gracious to a Nation.</hi> Ambition can propound nothing higher than to command the Creation, and this follows from the Friendſhip of Omnipotence. In Calamities the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine would be glad of a God too, to mend the ſtate of the World. Now whether we can apply the promiſes of the Old Teſtament or no, it's certain that the encouragement of preſent things is no ſuch ſtrange found under the Goſpel. <hi>Godlineſs has the promiſe of the life that now is,</hi> as well as of <hi>that which is to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. and if ever it be fulfilled <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> it will be to Politick Bodies, to Nations. Were there no more in it but the removing thoſe things that provoke God againſt us, it would deſerve all the good we can ſay of it. When a People have had the Goſpel ſo long, that they are aſhamed of it, and <hi>God ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98130:10"/> nigh unto them in all things,</hi> that they are weary of him; ſuch merciful viciſſitudes of Providence, and all preſently forgotten like ſome antediluvian Hiſtory; when Blaſphemy has corrupted the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of a Nation, and bold Exceſſes and Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation its Morals, the caſe of ſuch a People is not to be conſidered at a common rate. Had they been placed in ſome dark part of the World, they might with more ſafety have worſhipt the <hi>Pagods,</hi> and fallen down to the <hi>Riſing Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in ſuch publick Danger how uſeful would true Religion be in the hearts and lives of Men? One Property is, that it is full of Prayers, gets in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Gap, and will not ſuffer Deſtruction to break in. With all thoſe Cries of <hi>Sodom, Gen.</hi> 18. had there been but <hi>Ten Righteous Men</hi> to have mingled their Prayers, they had out-done them. Were then a <hi>Nation</hi> Religious, what a Security would this amount to? What an Harmony of publick Deſires, what ſtrong Cries? They do much now with all the noiſe of Blaſphemy; but were this the breathing of all our Souls, what a ſweet-ſmelling ſavour would it be? We ſhould with leſs Expence tread down our Enemies: and if it be a greater Bleſſing to have none, we ſhould have that too; for <hi>when a man's ways pleaſe the Lord, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth even his Enemies to be at peace with him, Prov.</hi> 16.7.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98130:10"/>
            <p>The reſult of all is, That we cheriſh our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as our <hi>Palladium.</hi> What <hi>Balak</hi> could not do by <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Inchantments he compaſſed by his Counſels, <hi>To lay a ſtumbling-block before the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>to eat things offered to Idols, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Fornication, Rev.</hi> 2.14. We have much the ſame Obligation to the debauched part of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nay, thô they talk high for the Government and Church, and give the Enemies of them to the Devil, they do ſo too by their own Souls and Blood every day. This helps not us, <hi>Hoc Ithacus velit.</hi> Let them reform their Lives, and we ſhall be glad of their Prayers, otherwiſe let them not name us. It looks like a deſperate Cauſe where they have any Intereſt. Let them take our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion altogether, or go ſeek one to which their Lives will be no ſcandal, but is as bad as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They deprive us of <hi>our Rock, our Strength, our Salvation,</hi> and inſtead of him they will defend us. Let them not miſtake us, (what <hi>Achiſh</hi> ſays in the caſe of <hi>David) Have we any need of Mad-men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sirs, it is our hard Fate that we have our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to deliver out of the hands of theſe Men as well as our moſt profeſſed Enemies. If it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, let us pray down their Blaſphemies. Yet Prayers themſelves will be but noiſe, except they be the Offerings of pure Minds, and our Lives
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98130:11"/> too be ſanctified to God. Thus we ſhall ſerve our Country better than in a Century of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagnes.</p>
            <p>But beſide a Perſonal Reformation, ſome have Families to bring in to the Common Service, ſome other Charges. And to Addreſs with all Reſpect to you, <hi>The Honourable and Worſhipful the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> you are <hi>Miniſters of God too,</hi> We are not forgetful how greatly you merited of us in times when it was not very ſafe to dare to be <hi>Engliſhmen.</hi> By you we do not look back with ſorrow upon the Ruins of a Nation, and cry, <hi>Fui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Troes.</hi> Only pardon me if I remember you that your worthy Conduct has raiſed our expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ſee the Laws againſt common wickedneſs better executed, and that you have not ſaved them in vain. Our Gracious Princes have not ſuch Deſigns as ſtand in need of the wickedneſs of their People. Stand up then for the Honour of God, who has imparted to you his Authority, and his Name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. Let not Vice bear it ſelf out with State and Quality, nor the <hi>floods of ungodly men make you afraid.</hi> We find that the naked Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Vertue will not do, and muſt beg your Hand for languiſhing Religion. Mark Vice with the Infamy the Laws have aſſigned it, reſtrain Atheiſm from Proſelyting in this Light, at leaſt frown all Profaneneſs out of gentile Society; let it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98130:11"/> be ſeen that you really <hi>hate the evil, and love the good,</hi> and we ſhall not take it ill if you call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us too in our turns, that we may all riſe up with united Zeal for the Honour of our God, for our Altars, for all our deareſt Intereſts, and for our afflicted Brethren, the <hi>Remnant of Joſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall conſider a Modern Prejudice againſt Religion. That <hi>good</hi> is to be <hi>loved,</hi> and <hi>evil hated,</hi> ſcarce any will deny; but the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity is, that what ſome Teachers of Religion call good, others call evil: ſo that ſome People think it reaſonable to be of none at all till they are agreed; which is ſo far from being to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that the ſame Teachers are not alway at agreement with themſelves, but what they call good at one time, they call evil another. 'Tis a ſcandal to ſome that a ſort of Doctrines taught ſo earneſtly a few years ago, are ſcarce now to be heard of, except with ſome temperaments and ſoftnings; 'tis a ſcandal to others that they were ever heard of. The iniquity of one Humour is unaccountable: The ſame People are angry with us for our ſcruples about the preſent Settlement and our compliances too; our Repentance is made our Crime; and if the Teachers of Religion know their buſineſs no better, it is no matter what any of them ſay: nothing is certain of it,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98130:12"/> but that it is all Cheat (<hi>Prieſtcraft</hi> is the Modiſh word), and in vain Men heat themſelves ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Fundamentals, for the time will come when they will take their turns too to be out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>This is the true ſtate of the Objection, which I could not decline, however it may ſeem to come in here. And indeed if all did not go to the account of Religion, we could be ſilent, thô we want not what to ſay for ſelves. We could in part deny the Fact. Men that never took the pains to underſtand our Doctrines, may bring us in for more than we taught; and becauſe we don't agree with their Fancies, think we do not agree with our ſelves. If we now leave the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Government to more proper Judges, in the main we teach the ſame Obedience to it. If this be done with leſs heat, it is becauſe the occaſion is ceaſed, and the Debaucheries of the Age (eſpecially the Objectors) find us ſufficient work. But my Deſign is not to vindicate our ſelves, but Religion; which I ſhall do upon a Suppoſition that what is contained in the Objection is true.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In general; Differences in Religion rightly conſidered, are a Confirmation to it: It has fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told them, <hi>There muſt be Hereſies,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.19.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98130:12"/> By this Rule <hi>Atticus</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> counted the <hi>Novatians</hi> good Witneſſes of the Common Faith<note n="(a)" place="margin">Soc. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note>. And thô the <hi>Marcionites</hi> ſeemed to be a ſcandal to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, yet God accepted the Confeſſions of ſome of them<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> de Martyr. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeſt. c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>; not becauſe they gave a Teſtimony to <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioniſm,</hi> but <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> 'Tis generally agreed among the Contending Parties, that there is one God, that there was ſuch a Perſon as Jeſus Chriſt, that the Hiſtories of the New Teſtament are for the main true, that there will be a Reſurrection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To turn the Argument upon them, if we may in any caſe prejudge, it is here in favour of Religion. Theſe muſt needs be Truths of great Evidence, which are preſerved among the heats of ſo many different Diſputes. Had we agreed in all little Particulars, they would have had the better colour to make a Plot of it. But the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that have been amongſt us from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Chriſtianity, do that Service as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute any ſuch Pretence. How would a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy have hung together of Men of ſuch contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sentiments, <hi>Paul</hi> againſt <hi>Peter, Barnabas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Paul,</hi> yet all ready to offer themſelves for their common Saviour? In the mean time how inconſiſtent are theſe People with themſelves?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98130:13"/> Sometimes we are all united in one Deſign to cheat the World: Sometimes we are ſo ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly contentious, that the ſafeſt way is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve none of us. So like are the Arguments of Sin to it ſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> full of Contradictions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſing that the Teachers of Religion had in ſome things altered their minds, this could only be an Argument againſt their Infallibility, which without all this trouble will be confeſt. We pretend to no other ways of coming at Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge than other Men, the uſe of means, which God bleſſes in ſeveral meaſures. Every Soul has its <hi>private reliſhes,</hi> a Natural kindneſs toward ſome Reaſons and Opinions more than others, which perhaps it brought from ſome former ſtate; and in this we are like the reſt of the World, till by good thinking we have recovered our ſelves. We have not an univerſal <hi>Genius,</hi> and it's no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if when we are out of our Province we run into ſome ſmall Errors. Beſide ſome things (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially relating to Government) may promiſe fair in the Speculation, but deceive in Practice, and are of ſuch a Nature, that they admit of no Proof but Experience. And as a Man is not preſently a Knave for not fore-ſeeing all Conſequences; ſo when tryal has ſhewed him the weakneſs of his Reaſons, it is ſo far from Crime, that I think he ought to forſake them.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98130:13"/>
            <p>But if the Teachers of Religion be ſo fallible, what Security have thoſe that are taught that they ſhall not be deceived? I Anſwer, <hi>You have</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, hear them.</hi> You have the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. We deny you no means that we have. You are not to expect new Oracles from us, and if in explaining the Old we corrupt them, you have them by you, <hi>Bring us to the Law and to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony;</hi> we decline not the Judgment of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt. Except you contribute by your own lazineſs, you are ſecure from Capital Errors; and thoſe which you cannot avoid by uſing all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible care and helps (of which we are but one part) ſhall never be Capital to you.</p>
            <p>But if Men can do all this themſelves, what need is there of Teachers? I Anſwer, This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds upon a wrong Notion of Teaching, which is not only bearing Men down with Authority, but leading them by Reaſon. 'Tis true, every Man muſt ſee for himſelf, but he that ſets a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a clear light to him, does him a ſervice. <hi>Call no man Maſter,</hi> take Religion upon no man's Credit, but we may from his Arguments. A very underſtanding Man has not always a good Reaſon at hand, yet can ſee and immediately embrace one when propounded. And this is the true uſe of Teaching in Religion, to help, not to ſuperſede your Enquiries.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98130:14"/>3. If we muſt needs go by prejudices, there are enough againſt thoſe that uſe theſe Inferences. Mind them, and you will certainly find, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are a <hi>lazy People</hi> that would fain throw all the trouble of their Salvation upon their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; or a ſort of <hi>empty peeviſh Diſputers,</hi> that for want of Argument begin to be angry, and throw dirt; or moſt commonly a <hi>vitious looſe Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> that would fain get rid of the reſtraints of Religion, and therefore catch at any preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt it. If it were not thus, they would apply the ſame Rule to other things as well as Religion. There are as many differences in Law; almoſt every Cauſe ſuppoſes one; is there there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no true ſenſe of it? Will they uſe no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician that was ever in an Error, or confeſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Mortal? I know of ſome Hereticks in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks, but it would be pity they ſhould ruin the Credit of Demonſtration. Nor will they ſay this, thô it be juſt the ſame Inference; which is a certain ſign they conſult their Luſts, and not their Reaſons in their Arguments againſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>However ſince Arguments work as they delight, not as they conclude, it would be well if we took them out of their hands. I wiſh our Differences were managed with more Candor and ingenuous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98130:14"/> allowance for the various inclinations of Souls. How happy are ſome of our Modern Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts if they can but make an Opinion, which they cannot ſolidly refute, look like ſome old He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, or ſhew how Atheiſts may make an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of it? This too often proves teaching of Atheiſm. We ſhould carefully avoid theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and making our Differences wider than they are. Add to this <hi>Ingenuity</hi> an <hi>Holy Life,</hi> and we ſecure our common Religion. Nor can Atheiſm find an Argument to delude with, after we have ſtript it of thoſe which our <hi>Conteſts</hi> and <hi>Vices</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it with.</p>
            <p>I have been ſo large upon this firſt Head of <hi>Religion,</hi> that I have left my ſelf but little room to ſpeak of <hi>Civil Juſtice.</hi> I ſhall therefore wave the <hi>common Arguments,</hi> and only in my way to a Concluſion lay before you the <hi>Obligation of Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Juſtice ſecures that Order by which Nations are eſtabliſh'd. The forming a Society conſiſts in the reſigning of private Will, and ſubmitting to one common Rule or Law. Its end is a general good, which yet will be fruſtrated, except there be ſome to put life into the Law by a vigorous execution. <hi>Cicero de Legib. l.</hi> 3. calls <hi>the Magiſtrate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98130:15"/> a ſpeaking Law, and the Law a mute Magiſtrate.</hi> But what if the Magiſtrate will not ſpeak, but is as mute as the Law? Then the one may paſs for a ſhadow of Power, the other for waſt Paper. The ſame Author calls <hi>Reaſon the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal and Eternal Law, the Law of the Gods;</hi> were it <hi>in effect</hi> the Law of <hi>Men</hi> too, a Nation might be Happy with a leſſer body of Statutes, and its Diſorders provided againſt by the quicker Methods of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, <hi>Quo judice nemo nocens abſolvitur,</hi> Juv Sat. 13. But this fits rather with the Idea's of ſome Romantick Common-wealth than the true ſtate of the World. We are in <hi>foece ſaeculi,</hi> where if Men do not ſuffer Juſtice ſometimes, they will do none. This would tame thoſe Men of Prey, the wicked in Power, when there ſhould be found thoſe who <hi>would break their jaws, and pluck the ſpoil out of their teeth,</hi> Job 29.17. Thoſe that know no ſuch thing as Property, will rather al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it than be Martyrs for their Opinion. The poor Man ſoweth in hope, becauſe he knows that thô his great Neighbour would enter upon his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, there is a greater than he, the Law. But when Innocency hath no defence but it ſelf, the poor comfort of <hi>Murus abeneus;</hi> when Cheating and Theft never ſin but in defect, <hi>viz.</hi> in not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made up a Sum worthy the conſideration of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98130:15"/> a Man of Place and Worſhip; when it comes to that, that <hi>Quae Turpia Cerdoni, Voleſos Brutoſque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebunt,</hi> Juv. Sat. 8. and the Merit of Men's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors ſhall ſave all their Race from Juſtice; no wonder if Treaſons, Rapines, and an increaſe of all Villany diſſolve the Society, and all runs back into Wilderneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It turns away God's Wrath from a Nation. God is honoured by Order, and where that is du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved it looks like his Kingdom. He is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in a Nation where Laws are like Copies of his Will, and Magiſtrates are as ambitious to reſemble him in Righteouſneſs as Power. The loins of the Poor ſhall bleſs us; we ſhall make Friends of the Protected Orphans; and thoſe that by our Juſtice have eſcaped Sycophantiſm, Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and other ways of Devouring, ſhall return it us in rich and fruitful Prayers. God is ſo pleaſed with Juſtice, that in the very inſtant of Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance it might make him drop his Thunder, and turn to the importunities of his ſofter Attributes. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> went a Whoring after the Gods and Daughters of <hi>Midian, Phinehas</hi> going a little out of the way to execute Judgment ſtai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging Plague, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.30 By the Promiſe made in the Text to the Houſe of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98130:16"/> Victorious <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> had never entred their <hi>Gates,</hi> had they but <hi>eſtabliſht Judgment</hi> there. It ſeems then it is a Fortification, as well as a <hi>Robe and Diadem,</hi> Job 29.</p>
            <p>You ſee now, <hi>Honourable and Worſhipful, and others entruſted with the Publick Juſtice,</hi> you ſee how much the Common Safety lies in your hands. Think your Native Country flies to your Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, your Mother in Tears, it's well not in Blood. Merit then a Crown, the Honour not only <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vati Civis</hi> but <hi>Civitatis.</hi> Dare to be Juſt; not frighted at a mighty Malefactor; ſuch make a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sacrifice and a better Example. Like the hand of the Heroick <hi>Phineh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> know no Quality, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>Zimries</hi> will laugh at your Title of Gods, and play with the <hi>Sword you bear in vain.</hi> Thoſe that deſtroy us are zealous, they fear not the Day nor Law; and ſhall thoſe in whoſe hands our Peace is entruſted, fear to be ſingularly good, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve upon each other the Honour of Beginning? Rejoyce then, O ye Libertines, ye aſſerters of Nature!</p>
            <p>But in commending Zeal we do not encourage all the Heats and Fits that Humane Minds are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. A clear Zeal for Juſtice can hardly be carried too high, but we muſt have a care we do not miſtake our Paſſions for it. Even Zeal for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98130:16"/> your own way of worſhipping God may ſometimes be out of place, when it runs into tranſports a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that are protected by the ſame Laws with our ſelves. What ſhould I ſay more of other Corruptions ſo much below your Character? Perhaps I have ſaid too much already to Perſons of your approved Conduct.</p>
            <p>I will only ſpeak a word with thoſe that ſhall come here upon their Oaths, and I have done. You touch the Goſpels out of which you ſhall one day be judged; you call a Juſt and Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>God for a Record upon your Souls:</hi> what is the ſenſe of all this if you falſifie, but that you put your hands to your own Damnation? As I take it, you that are upon the Juries repreſent your Country; it will have but little reaſon to thank you for the Service, if you involve it in Perjury and the Curſe of God. Yet there are ſhameful ſtories in the World about prepared Witneſſes and made Juries. Sure Men kiſs the Book they never read. Do your endeavour to recover the Credit of our Conſtitution and of Chriſtianity, deliver us and your own Souls. And may God direct all that are concerned in this Aſſembly ſo to diſcharge themſelves, as expecting aſſuredly one day to render an Account in a more fearful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, when God ſhall Judge the World; that ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98130:17"/> the Publick Intereſts may receive no check from what ſhall be tranſacted here. And let us all unite in ſuch an <hi>hatred to Evil, and love to Good,</hi> and ſo do our parts in our ſeveral Stations <hi>to the eſtabliſhing of Juſtice,</hi> that God may be glorified by us, and delighted in us, and as he has begun, may continue <hi>to be gracious to the Remnant of</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Samuel Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. <hi>1691.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Aſſizes held at <hi>Horſham</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex, Auguſt</hi> 23d. 1691. Before the Honourable Sir <hi>William Dolben,</hi> Knight, one of the Juſtices of the Court of <hi>King's-Bench.</hi> By <hi>Richard Lucas,</hi> D. D. Vicar of St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s <hi>Coleman-ſtreet, London.</hi> In 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Enquiry after Happineſs, Vol. the Firſt, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1685. Price 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The true Notion of Humane Life: Or, A Second Part of the Enquiry after Happineſs, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1690. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Servants:</hi> Containing, Firſt, The Parents Duty, how to Educate their Children, that they may be fit to be employod and truſted. Second, What Preparation is needful for ſuch as are entring into Service, with ſome Rules to be obſerved by them, how to make a wiſe and happy Choice of a Service. 3. Their Duty in Service towards <hi>God,</hi> their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and <hi>Themſelves;</hi> together with ſuitable Prayers to each Duty, and ſome Directions peculiarly to Servants for the Worthy Receiving the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Publiſhed for the Benefit of Families, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All written by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>The Wiſdom of God manifeſted in the Works of the Creation, By <hi>Jo. Ray,</hi> M. A. Fellow of the Royal Society, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1691. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A New Hiſtory of the <hi>Roman</hi> Conclave: Containing the Rites and Ceremonies uſed and obſerved at the Death, Election, and Coronation of the <hi>Pope:</hi> As alſo an Exact Deſcription of the ſtate of <hi>Rome,</hi> during the Vacancy of that Chair. Together with a Brief Account of the Life of this preſent Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> XII. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> 1691.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98130:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
